Nathan DeVrio

Human-Computer Interaction PhD Student, Carnegie Mellon University

407 S Craig St Pittsburgh, PA 15213 (571)-499-3442 ⋈ ndevrio@cmu.edu www.nriopelle.me

Research Interests

I research the next generation of interactive hardware technologies to address limitations in performance, capability, and usability. New devices should not just fix the shortcomings reported by users of current ones but also enable previously impossible and delightful forms of interaction.

Technical Areas: Human-Computer Interaction, Sensors, Activity Recognition, AR/VR, Ubiquitous Computing

Education

2020 - Present Carnegie Mellon University,

Pittsburgh, PA Human-Computer Interaction Institute, PhD in Human-Computer Interaction.

2016 - 2020 University of Michigan,

Ann Arbor, MI Bachelors of Science in Engineering in Computer Engineering,

Summa Cum Laude.

GPA: 3.94/4.00

Professional Experience

2020 - Present Future Interfaces Group, Carnegie Mellon University, PhD Student,

Pittsburgh, PA Advisor: Chris Harrison

Creating novel sensing devices for aiding in interaction tasks. The technical areas that I specialize in include sensor hardware design, embedded programming, and machine learning for sensor data.

Summer 2023 Meta Reality Labs, AR/VR Input Technologies, Research Scientist Intern (PhD),

Redmond, WA Advisors: Roger Boldu, Wolf Kienzle, Eric Whitmire

Researched ways to use sensors to enable interactions with the next generation of AR and VR devices..

2018 - 2020 Interactive Sensing and Computing Lab, University of Michigan, Undergraduate Researcher,

Ann Arbor, MI Advisor: Alanson Sample

Designed a wrist-worn device to detect different ways a user interacts with objects or surfaces and determine their activity by measuring properties of the body and the environment.

Summer 2019 Microsoft Corporation, Azure Storage Media and Edge, SWE Intern,

Redmond, WA Mentor: Aniket Malatpure

Developed a root-cause analysis pipeline for Azure Stack. Published a research paper describing the how the dependency graph algorithm I wrote could be applied to any private cloud system.

Summer 2018 Microsoft Corporation, Azure Storage Media and Edge, SWE Intern,

Bellevue, WA Mentors: Aniket Malatpure, Suman Nath

Integrated an instrumentation tool prototyped by Microsoft Research for discovering hard-to-find fault injection and thread-safety bugs earlier in development into product code for Azure Stack.

2017 - 2018 Robert Dick Group, University of Michigan, Undergraduate Researcher,

Ann Arbor, MI Advisor: Robert Dick

Developed an embedded sensing and actuation device for aiding anesthesiologists in improving the accuracy and efficiency of epidural procedures by identifying when the needle is approaching bone.

- Summer 2017 The MITRE Corporation, Electronic System Dev, Embedded Software Intern,
- Bedford, MA Mentors: Rachel Bainbridge, Chris Niessen

Researched electromagnetic fault injection attacks on cryptographic algorithms implemented on FPGAs. Led a team in an intern embedded security capture the flag competition and placed in the top 5 teams.

2016 - 2017 Lab11, University of Michigan, Undergraduate Researcher,

Ann Arbor, MI Advisors: Prabal Dutta, Branden Ghena

Resolved errors in the preexisting implementation of a Bluetooth low-energy embedded audio sensor. Redesigned the device after performing power analytics to bring the project to an operational state.

Summer 2015 U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, Laboratory for Autonomous Systems Research, Robotics Intern, Washington, D.C. Mentor: Donald Sofge

Used bat-like echolocation delivered via an FPGA sensor platform to identify different terrains an autonomous robot encountered. Published a research paper on my approach and experimental results.

Publications

Conference Papers

- C.06 *N. DeVrio, *V. Mollyn, C. Harrison, SmartPoser: Arm Pose Estimation With a Smartphone and Smartwatch Using UWB and IMU Data. In Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2023).
- C.05 N. DeVrio, C. Harrison, DiscoBand: Multiview Depth-Sensing Smartwatch Strap for Hand, Body, and Environment Tracking. In Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST 2022).
- C.04 K. Ahuja, V. Shen, C. Fang, N. Riopelle, A. Kong, C. Harrison, ControllerPose: Inside-Out Body Capture with VR Controller Cameras. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Human Factors in Computing, (CHI 2022)
- C.03 V. Varga, G. Vakulya, B. Buergisser, N. Riopelle, F. Zund, R. Sumner, T. Gross, A. Sample, Real-Time Interaction Capture through Physical Contact for Mixed Reality. *In Proceedings of the International Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction*, (TEI 2021)
- C.02 N. Riopelle, A. Malatpure, S. Ashtekar, V. Raman, Dependency Graph-based Failure Analysis for Private Clouds. In Proceedings of the International Symposium on Software Reliability Engineering, (ISSRE 2019)
- C.01 N. Riopelle, P. Caspers, D. Sofge, Terrain Classification for Autonomous Vehicles Using Bat-Inspired Echolocation. In Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Neural Networks, (IJCCN 2018) Posters
- P.01 **N. Riopelle**, A. Sample, ActiMate: A Wrist-Based, Heterogeneous Sensor Platform for Recognizing User Activities and Routines. *University of Michigan Engineering Research Symposium*, Nov 8, 2019

Awards

- 2021 NSF GRFP Honorable Mention.
- 2020 UM EECS Department Outstanding Research Award.
- 2019 UM EECS Department Outstanding Achievement Award.
- 2019 UM EECS Scholar Award.
- 2019 UM Henry Ford II Prize Nominee (from Computer Engineering).
- 2018, 2019 UM James B. Angell Scholar.
 - 2017 UM William J. Branstrom Freshman Prize.
- 2016 2020 UM Dean's List.
- 2016 2020 UM University Honors.

Invited Talks & Panels

2022 Alumni Panel Member, Connect with Michigan ECE.

Service

2021 - 2023 Student Volunteer, Carnegie Mellon Graduate Application Support Program.

2022 - Present Paper Reviewer, CHI Conference.

2022 Student Volunteer, CHI Conference.

Teaching Experience & Mentorship

- 2022 **05-435/865 Applied Fabrication for HCI**, Teaching Assistant.
- 2020 EECS 598-015 Engineering Interactive Systems, Instructional Aide.

2022 Mentored Vimal Mollyn, Master's student.

2023 Invited Talk, Brown HCI.